A Inventory of the African pictorial collection, 1889-1994
Hoover Institution Archives
African Pictorial Collection
1889-1994
XX040
95 envelopes, 2 manuscript boxes, 1 album box, 6 slide boxes, 1 oversize folder (11.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Photographs, postcards, and slides, depicting scenes of daily life, cultural and historical sites, prominent personalities, and works of art in various countries of Africa.
Administrative Information
Access
The collection is open for research
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives. An increment was added in 2011.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Scope and Content of Collection
Photographs, postcards, and slides, depicting scenes of daily life, cultural and historical sites, prominent personalities, and works of art in various countries of Africa.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in Stanford University's online catalog.
Subjects
Art--Africa.; Africa--Pictorial works.
Container List
- 3 prints of Nigeria; 14 prints of Uganda; 1 print and 1 negative of the White Nile in southern Sudan. (File mA)
- 3 prints of Zaire; 1 print of Madagascar; 1 print of Rhodesia; 1 unidentified print. (File B)
- 49 prints of Zaire. (File C)
- 10 prints of Rhodesia. (File D)
- 1 print of Tanzania; 7 prints of Zaire; 1 print of South Africa (Cape Province); 1 print of Zambia (Barotseland); 7 prints of Madagascar; 1 print and 1 negative of Southern Rhodesia; 1 print of Northern Rhodesia; 1 print of Nigeria; 1 print of Lord Delamere, Kenya; 1 print of President Philibert Tsiranana, Malagasy; 1 print of Ghana; 3 prints of the Seychelles; 1 print of Ndebele women. (File E)
- 27 prints of Gabon; 1 print of Zaire; 1 print of the Ivory Coast. (File F)
- 32 prints of the Ivory Coast. (File G)
- 85 prints of Rhodesia. (File H)
- 57 prints of Angola; 58 prints Sao Tome. (File I)
- 1 print of Zairel 1 print of Lake Tanganyika; 1 print of Rhodesia; 37 prints of drawings depicting the colonization of Africa by the Portuguese; 1 unidentified print. (File J)
- 51 prints of Mozambique, 2 postcards of Mozambique, 1 print of Guinea; 40 prints of Portuguese officials. 1 print of Angolan officials; 1 print of Guinean official. (File K)
- 1 print of meroe; 2 prints of Zambia; 2 prints of drawings of the Ashanti wars; 1 print of Ethiopia; 1 print of the Ivory Coast; 2 prints of Angola. (File L)
- 58 prints of Rhodesia. (File M)
- 13 prints of Mozambique; 36 prints of Angola; 1 print of the Benguela Railroad; 3 unidentified prints. (File N)
- 1 map of the Nile River; 51 prints of Rhodesia; 1 print of the Grand Vizier of Bauchi, Nigeria; 2 prints of cartoons of Cecil Rhodes; 1 print of Cecil Rhodes; 1 print of Francois Guillard (?); 2 prints of Sir Harry H. Johnston. (File O)
- 1 print of Holman Bentley, Zaire; 6 prints of Zaire; 2 prints of Rhodesia. (File P)
- 2 prints of paintings, South Africa; 8 filmstrips. (File Q)
- 61 negatives of scenes, people, and art work of Africa. (File R-W)
- 22 negatives of African scenes, people, painting. (File X)
- 44 negatives of African scenes, people, painting. (File Y-BB)
- 68 prints of Rhodesia, 1971. (File CC)
- 24 prints of Angola; 14 prints of Portuguese and African officials; 6 prints of Zaire. (File DD)
- 9 prints of Historical Africa (File EE)
  (5 prints of Zimbabwe; 2 prints of Naletale; 1 map of Ghana, Mali and Songhai Empires; 1 miscellaneous print).
- 7 prints of Historical Africa (File FF)
  (3 prints of Meroe; 1 print of Faras West; 1 print of Debeira West; 1 print of Serra; 1 print of Kilwa)
- 14 prints of Historical Africa (File GG)
  (1 print of Timbuktu; 2 prints of Lalibela; 4 prints of Axum; 2 prints of Debeira West; 1 print of Portuguese fortifications; 3 unidentified prints; 1 map of Southeast Africa).
- 6 prints of The Land (File HH)
  (1 print of West Africa; 1 print of Kenya; 1 print of Chad; 3 prints of North Africa.
- 9 prints of the Land (File II)
  (3 prints of Kenya; 1 print of Lake Chad; 1 print of Uganda; 1 print of Ruanda-Urundi; 1 print of Tanzania; 1 print of Kegera National Park; 1 unidentified print).
- 10 prints of The Land (File JJ)
  (2 prints of South Africa; 2 prints of Victoria Falls; 1 print of Zambia; 1 print of Timbuktu; 4 unidentified print).
- 10 prints of African Art and Design. (File KK)
- 9 prints of African Art and Design. (File LL)
- 11 prints of African Art and Design. (File MM)
- 6 prints of the people of Africa. (File NN)
- 7 prints of the People of Africa. (File OO)
- 9 prints of the Lives and Livelihoods of Africa. (File PP)
- 10 prints of the lives and Livelihoods of Africa. (File QQ)
- 9 prints of the lives and Livelihoods of Africa. (File RR)
- 12 prints of the lives and Livelihoods of Africa. (File SS)
- 4 prints of African wood carvings from Zaire. (File TT)
- 21 prints of historical Africa (File UU)
  (primarily scenes in Rhodesia, South Africa, and the Congo. Also prints of Portuguese explorers)
- 9 prints of the people of Africa. (File VV)
- 34 prints of African Art and Design. (File WW)
- 20 prints of African Art and Design. (File XX)
- 9 prints of the land. (File YY)
- 21 prints depicting forces of the Revolutionary Government of Angola, aiding villagers and on military maneuvers. (File ZZ)
- 101 prints depicting daily life, public buildings, cultural and scenic sites in French Africa, including Niger, Mauritania, Ivory Coast, mali Senegal, Central African Republic, Togo, Chad, Congo, Cameroun and Malagasy Republic. (File AAA)
- 88 prints of Mozambique (File BBB-MMM)
- 80 prints of South Africa, Rhodesia and Namibia, entitled "Southern Africa, the Imprisoned Society," depicting people and events. Compiled and published by the International Defence and Aid Fund for Southern Africa London. (File fNNN)
- 12 prints depicting living conditions in Soweto, the area reserved for Black South Africans outside of Johannesburg, October, 1982. (File OOO)
- 12 color slides depicting various places of interest in Angola, 1975, set in a descriptive catalog. (File PPP)
- 100 color slides depicting works of African art, based on an exhibition held in the Museum of Anthropology, University of California, Berkeley, April 6 – October 22, 1967. (File QQQ-VVV)
  Captions Available.
- 8 prints of posters, newspapers, and books, used for the African Collection brochure, 1984. (File WWW)
- 3 prints (postcards) relating to the Frente Popular para la Liberacion de Sajuia el Hamra y Rio de Oro (POLISARIO), C. 1981 (File XXX)
  W. Sahara.
- 9 prints relating to the POLISARIO movement, c. 1977 (File mYYY)
  Western Sahara.
- 7 prints relating to the POLISARIO movement, c. 1977 (File mZZZ)
  Western Sahard.
- 3 prints depicting the Bechuanaland Trading Association store, Livingstone, c. 1905; the L.F. Moore Chemist shop, Livingstone; and palaver between Lewanika and F. E. Lochner on behalf of the British South Africa Co., 1890. (File AAAA)
- 1 mounted print depicting Vice President George Bush at a State dinner for President Kenneth Kaunda of Zambia. (File M*BBBB)
- 3 prints depicting missionaries preaching in Africa at the turn of the century. (File CCCC)
- 2 prints of the University of Witwatersrand; 1 off-campus anti-apartheid sign. 2 postal cards of Amilcar Cabral. 3 prints of Kaiser engineers construction projects in Africa: 1 in Ghana on the Volta River, 1 in Guinea relating to exploration for iron ore, 1 in the Ivory Coast's hydroelectric projects. (File DDDD)
- 6 postcards, n.d.: 2 depicting Mukaru Ng'Ang'A and Wanyiri Kihoro, political prisoners in Kenya; 2 depicting views of Sierra Leone; 1 depicting villagers assembled for work duty in Zaire during Belgian rule; and 1 advertizing the book Das alte Sudwestafriika by H. Vedder, a history of Namibia until 1890. (File EEEE)
- 11 greeting cards, 1987, and 17 postcards, n.d., issued by the African national Congress and other anti-apartheid organizations, depicting Nelson and Winnie Mandela and other South African militants; and 1 postcard, n.d., depicting the Palace of justice in Pretoria, South Africa. (File FFFF)
- 1 greeting card, n.d., depicting a mural by Malangatana Ngwenya entitled "The People's Struggle in the Context of Nature"; and 5 postcards, 1979, celebrating the 4th anniversary of Mozambique's independence. (File GGGG)
- 1 print, 1969, depicting Wakamba dancers at the Kenya Safari Club in Nairobi. (File HHHH)
- 2 prints, 1989 depicting President Sam Nujoma's first address in 30 years to the South West Africa People's Organization within the borders of Namibia. (File IIII)
- 15 prints, 1964-1968, depicting the Peoples Republic of China's influence in Tanzania and Ethiopia and the 1964 Zanzibar coup. (File JJJJ)
  Includes 1 print of Chou En Lai and 2 prints of President Julius Nyerere.
- 23 postcards depicting southern African culture and politics (File KKKK)
- 39 prints depicting the drought in northern Africa. (File LLLL)
- 36 prints depicting society in rural Ghana. (File MMMM)
- 1 print depicting Cyril Ramaphosa, Secretary-General of the African National Congress. (File NNNN)
- 3 prints depicting Mozambique Liberation Front (FRELMO) soldiers, 1972. (File OOOO)
- 3 prints of President Issaya Afeworki of Eritrea and other Eritrean officials, 1993; and 5 postcards of scenes in Eritrea. (File PPPP)
- 2 prints of election posters in Walvis Bay, Namibia, 1992. (File QQQQ)
- 11 postcards of buildings in Guinea-Bissau, n.d. (File RRRR)
- 9 postcards of scenes from the colonial period in the Ivory Coast, n.d. (File SSSS)
- 8 postcards depicting scenes related to the struggle for independence in Eritrea (File TTTT)
- 21 postcards depicting leaders and posters of the African National Congress, 1987-1990. (File UUUU)
- 32 postcards depicting miscellaneous African scenes, many of them from the colonial period. (File VVVV)
- 56 color photographs of election posters and election scenes in South Africa, 1994. (File WWWW)
- 7 postcards depicting the people and culture of Botswana (File XXXX)
- 1 postcard of the mosque of Djenne, Mali, 1989. (File YYYY)
- 7 folders of soldiers, weapons, victims, and damage in the Angolan civil war, n.d. Postcard of Jomo Kenyatta, n.d. 8 prints of demonstrations in Uganda against United Nations Intervention in the Congo (Leopoldville), 1965. (Box 1)
- Incremental Materials (Box 2)
  This addition to the collection has not yet been described. Please let the Hoover Institution Archives know if you would like to see this material described. Contact us at hooverarchivesinfo@stanford.edu